Welcome back. In this lesson, we're going to learn about abstract classes and abstract methods in TypeScript.
These are powerful tools using real-world applications to enforce structure, consistency,
and design rules across our codebase. If you've ever wanted to have frameworks
for us to implement certain methods, this is how they do it. Let's start with a problem.
Imagine we're building an application with different types of uses.
Apps, admins, regular users, and maybe guests. All users should have a login method,
but the actual implementation might be different for each type.
So we're going to need some shared structure, some different implementations and enforce rules.
And that's exactly where abstract classes come in.
An abstract class is a class that cannot be instantiated directly. It's meant to be extended
by other classes. Abstract classes define what must exist, but not necessary how it works.
Let's go to an example. So we do use the abstract keyword to abstract class and then user.
We then provide a constructor. Our constructor might have a username, so let's do a public username,
but type of string. Let's just leave the constructor blank at the moment.
And now we want to define our mandatory method. We do abstract and then do login.
This is our method and our method is going to return nothing, so basically void.
So we define an abstract class called user.
We notice that we use the abstract keyword here.
Also notice that the login method has no body. So this method must be implemented by any class
that extends user. So abstract methods enforce a contract. They guarantee that every subclass
provides its own implementation. Again, if any subclass inherits from this particular masterclass,
it must implement this particular method. If a subclass forgets implement this method,
TypeScript is going to throw an error before our code even runs. Let's now do an example.
So we do class and then admin user, and we say extends, extends our masterclass of user.
Let's hover over and we see that TypeScript forces us to implement this particular method.
So now let's do login. This returns a void. Now we can do whatever we want. So it perhaps
console log and say log in.
So in this example, the admin user extends user and is required to implement the login methods.
Let's now create another user type. Let's do one called regular user.
So class regular user extends user. Once again, TypeScript is going to force us to implement
this method. I'm just going to copy this method and paste it into here.
Now if class is full of the same structure, but that behavior can differ. So of course,
if we don't want to do this, we could say have a logged in regular user.
And now we can actually create our classes. So we could do const admin equals new admin user,
and we can provide a string, perhaps Alice, and we can then do the same thing for the regular user
and do const user equals new regular user and say bob. And now we can do admin dot log in
user dot log in. Even though we can't create instances of the abstract user class directly,
we can work with subclasses. So if we try and do something like this and do const test user
equals new user, we're going to get this message that we can't create an instance of the abstract
class. Now a common question is why not just use an interface? But there are some differences
between it. In an abstract class, we can have constructors. We can have implemented methods
and make an store state. Whereas in interfaces, we don't actually have any implementation.
We have no constructors, and it's basically pure structure. So again, if we have an abstract class,
we can define some default behavior in our actual master class, which we can't do when we're
using an interface because we can't have any implementation. They use an interface when you only
need structure, easily abstract class, when you need to have shared logic plus enforce rules.
Now abstract classes can also contain regular methods. Let's just blast us away and do another example.
Let's define a class called shape. So abstract class of shape.
Now let's define a shared method to abstract area. This can return a number.
Now we can define another method perhaps called describe, describe.
This returns nothing, and we can do a little implementation here in say console, log, and say
this is a shape. So this area method here, because it's marked by abstract,
must be implemented by subclasses. What this method here describe is already implemented and shared.
It doesn't necessarily have to be implemented. So let's try and implement this straight shape.
We can define another class called circle, let me say extends shape. We can create a constructor
and we can say for example private, radius, subtype number.
So we can define our own constructor on our class. And then we need to call the super
to call the constructor if it's defined on the shape, rotate super.
And now if you hover over it, it says we must declare this method called area.
So let's do that. And the area returns a number.
Now we can do return math dot pi times this dot radius times this dot radius.
So our circle class must implement the area method, or we get the error, which we saw,
but it automatically inherits that describe method.
Let's talk about some real world use classes. So abstract classes are commonly used in
things like framework based classes, game engines, UI components, or maybe API service layers.
They allow large teams to follow consistent rules while still allowing flexibility.
So abstract classes to find what must be done, not necessarily how it's done.
And there are powerful ways to enforce structure and build scalable TypeScript applications.